Register of the Chilean Subject Collection, 1933-1999
Hoover Institution Archives
Chilean Subject Collection,
1933-1999
XX777
11 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 phonorecord, 110 slides, 2 phonotape cassettes (8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, bulletins, press releases, minutes, resolutions, campaign material, and printed matter, relating to the presidency of Salvador Allende and the military coup of 1973 in Chile; subsequent political, economic and human rights conditions in Chile; the Chilean plebiscite of 1988 and elections of 1989 and 1992; and communist political movements in Chile.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Allende Gossens, Salvador, 1908-1973.; Chile--Politics and government--1970-1973.; Chile--History--Coup d' etat, 1973.; Chile--Politics and government--1973-; Elections--Chile.; Civil rights--Chile.; Communism--Chile.; Communism.; Chile.; Phonorecords.; Slides (Photography); Phonotapes.
Series Description
- Subject File, 1933-1999 (Boxes 1-8)
  Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, position papers, bulletins, press releases, charts, serial issues, newsletters, flyers, campaign material, circulars, speeches, opinion polls, biographical sketches, clippings, minutes, resolutions, charts, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject
- Oversize File, 1972-1989 (Boxes 9-10)
  Clippings, serial issues, handbills, and miscellaneous election material
- Audiovisual File, n.d. and 1970 (Record cabinet, Slide cabinet)
  One phonorecord relating to the massacre of striking nitrate miners in 1907; 110 slides used in a literacy campaign
Container List
- SUBJECT FILE, 1933-1993
  - General. Reports, pamphlets, serial issues, bulletins, circular, and clippings, 1969-1992. SEE ALSO: AUDIOVISUAL FILE (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - General (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Allende administration. Letter, pamphlets, reports, newsletters, correspondence, charts, and flyers; includes material relating to agricultural development, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Armed Forces. Reprints, 1988 (Folder 3)
  - Direccion de Inteligencia Nacional (DINA). Serial issue giving details of secret archives of the Chilean intelligence service, 1993. Includes information on the assassination of General Carlos Prats (Folder 4)
  - Drugs. Speech by Javier Illanes, 1988(?). (Folder 5)
  - Economics. Reports and newsletters, 1979-1993. Includes statistical data and macroeconomic analyses (Folder 6)
  - Human rights
    - General. Clippings, speech, leaflet, pamphlet, report, instructional material, 1977-1990 (Folder 7)
    - United Nations Commission on Human Rights. Correspondence and reports, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Leftist organizations. Program statements, pamphlets, bulletins, and serial issues, 1943-1987. Includes press releases and bulletins issued by Russia, China, and the National Liberation Front (Vietnam) (Folder 4-5)
  - Movimiento de Izquierda Revolucionaria (MIR). Speeches, program statements, flyers, serial issues, and newsletters, 1969-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Movimiento de Izquierda Revolucionaria (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Partido Comunista de Chile. Reports, pamphlets, flyers, circulars, and newsletters, 1976-1987 (Folder 3-5)
  - Partido Comunista de Chile (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Partido Socialista de Chile. Program statements, flyers, serial issues, pamphlets, and newsletters, 1981-1988 (Folder 2)
  - Politics
    - General. Statutes, pamphlets, program statements, and serial issues, 1933-1989. Includes material relating to fascist organizations in Chile (Folder 3-4)
    - Plebiscite, 1988. Reports and newsletter, 1988 (Folder 5)
    - Elections
      - 1989
        - General. Pamphlets, statutes, serial issues, electoral guide, opinion polls, clippings, program statements, newsletter, and miscellany, 1989 (Folder 6)
        - General (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
        - Concertacion por la Democracia. Program statements, clippings, and miscellany, primarily relating to the presidential candidacy of Patricio Aylwin Azocar, 1989 (Folder 4)
        - Conservative parties. Program statements, clippings, biographical sketches, and miscellany, primarily relating to the candidacies of Hernan Buchi Buc and Francisco Errazuriz Talavera, 1989 (Folder 5)
      - 1992. Flyers, leaflets, and miscellany, 1992 (Folder 6)
  - Youth organizations (primarily leftist). Reports, position papers, clippings, correspondence (including communist youth organizations in other countries), meeting materials, flyers, resolutions, pamphlets, newsletters, poems, and miscellany; includes material relating to the Juventudes Comunistas de Chile, Juventud Democrata Cristiana, Movimiento de Izquierda Revolucionaria, and Pablo Neruda, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 1-9)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1972-1989.
  - Clippings, serial issues, handbills, and miscellaneous election material (Box 9-10)
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, n.d. and 1970.
  - One phonorecord, "The Siege of Santa Maria de Iquique: A People's Cantata of the Chilean Nitrate Miners," performed by Quilapayun, 1970 (Record-cabinet Record cabinet)
  - 110 slides used in a literacy campaign (Slide-cabinet Slide cabinet)